<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on A Hugo website</title>
    <link>/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on A Hugo website</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 26 May 2015 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Zero-inflated Poisson from complex samples</title>
      <link>/2015/05/26/zero-inflated-poisson-from-complex-samples/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 May 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2015/05/26/zero-inflated-poisson-from-complex-samples/</guid>
      <description>A very long post about how to add models to the survey package; specifically, the zero-inflated Poisson.
The Zero-Inflated Poisson model is a model for count data with excess zeros. The response distribution is a mixture of a point mass at zero and a Poisson distribution: if \(Z\) is Bernoulli with probability \(1-p_0\) and \(P\) is Poisson with mean \(\lambda\) then
\[Y=Z+(1-Z)P\]
is zero-inflated Poisson. The ZIP is a latent-class model; we can have \(Y=0\) either because \(Z=0\) or because \(P=0\).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Call me, Ishmael</title>
      <link>/2015/05/20/call-me-ishmael/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 May 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2015/05/20/call-me-ishmael/</guid>
      <description>Making small changes in text to escape plagiarism-detection software is challenging but not really difficult. The relationship between your text and the urtext in the software is precise and syntactic; the software doesn’t know about ideas. Making small changes in a text that change or obscure the meaning is also easy, and is why copyeditors exist. Making small changes in a text that give an interesting new meaning is enormously harder, as in the opening of Peter de Vries’ “The Vale of Laughter”, quoted as the title of this post.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Superefficiency</title>
      <link>/2015/05/12/superefficiency/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 May 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2015/05/12/superefficiency/</guid>
      <description>If you have \(X_1,\ldots,X_n\) independent from an \(N(\mu,1)\) distribution you don’t have to think too hard to work out that \(\bar X_n\), the sample mean, is the right estimator of \(\mu\) (unless you have quite detailed prior knowledge). As people who have taken an advanced course in mathematical statistics will know, there is a famous estimator that appears to do better. Hodges’ estimator is given by \(H_n=\bar X_n\) if \(|\bar X_n|&amp;gt;n^{-1/4}\), and \(H_n=0\) if \(|\bar X_n|\leq n^{-1/4}\).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Precise answers, but not necessarily to the right question</title>
      <link>/2015/05/04/precise-answers-but-not-necessarily-to-the-right-question/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 May 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2015/05/04/precise-answers-but-not-necessarily-to-the-right-question/</guid>
      <description>Nicholas Schork has a commentary at Nature about precision medicine, arguing in favour of n-of-1 trials. These are the extreme version of crossover trials: you randomise each individual to a long sequence of periods on each of two treatments and see which they do better on. The idea makes sense: you get genuinely individual-specific results for people in the study, and the ability to aggregate them to generalise to people not in the study.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What’s the right proof of the Continuous Mapping Theorem?</title>
      <link>/2015/05/03/whats-the-right-proof-of-the-continuous-mapping-theorem/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 May 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2015/05/03/whats-the-right-proof-of-the-continuous-mapping-theorem/</guid>
      <description>The Continuous Mapping Theorem says that if \(X_n\stackrel{d}{\to}X\) and \(f\) is continuous except at a set of points with zero probability under \(X\), that \(f(X_n)\stackrel{d}{\to}f(X)\). As David Pollard points out, it should be called the almost-everywhere-continuous mapping theorem, because the ability to have discontinuities is important in applications and is the only thing making the proof non-trivial. There are three proofs that I’m aware of
Mann and Wald used the ‘pointwise convergence of cdfs’ definition of convergence in distribution, which gives a painful proof</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Eppur si muove</title>
      <link>/2015/04/02/eppur-si-muove/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2015/04/02/eppur-si-muove/</guid>
      <description>“The rules for winning the science competition focus on a small number of measures that incentivize poor practice” Hilda Bastian quoting Ottoline Leyser.
It’s all true, and more and worse besides. Researchers are driven by the incentives for high-impact publication; p-value hacking makes results seem more convincing than they are; trials use surrogate outcomes; glamour journals publish insufficiently-checked linkbait; predatory online journals will do anything for money; change and decay in all around we see.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pharmacy ethics</title>
      <link>/2015/03/29/pharmacy-ethics/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2015/03/29/pharmacy-ethics/</guid>
      <description>‘You have heard that it was said to those of ancient times, “You shall not murder”; and “whoever murders shall be liable to judgement.” But I say to you that if you are angry with a brother or sister, you will be liable to judgement. Matthew 5:21-22
In practice, we have to distinguish. Whoever murders is liable to judgement, but being angry isn’t enough. In the same way, formal codes of professional ethics come in two versions: the aspirational code that describes the way we want the profession to be, and the legalistic code that describes what will get you kicked out.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Paper helicopters at a science fair</title>
      <link>/2015/03/28/paper-helicopters-at-a-science-fair/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2015/03/28/paper-helicopters-at-a-science-fair/</guid>
      <description>Today, we ran Box’s paper helicopter experimental design example at the Science Street Fair sponsored by the NZ Association of Scientists and hosted by the Museum of Transport and Technology.
It went fairly well. In particular, the younger kids really liked dropping paper helicopters and comparing different designs and we got in a few useful discussions of experimental design with adults – mostly school teachers.
Things to note:
 Use a photocopier and pre-printed design template, such as the one from the SixSigma package for R This lets you also produce a 2-up version, giving an extra interesting design factor.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What does measurability mean?</title>
      <link>/2015/03/07/what-does-measurability-mean/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2015/03/07/what-does-measurability-mean/</guid>
      <description>Attention conservation notice: A long, meandering, and inconclusive attempt to explain why you perhaps shouldn’t worry about a technical issue you almost certainly weren’t worrying about already. 
Mathematical proofs in statistics are, in some formal sense, useless. That is, they formally have conditions such as finite moments, boundedness, differentiability or stochastic equicontinuity that either apply to all things in the real world or to none. The proofs are also often formally about infinite sequences; these don’t crop up all that often in data analysis.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How hard did you look: equivalence and non-inferiority</title>
      <link>/2015/02/27/how-hard-did-you-look-equivalence-and-non-inferiority/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2015/02/27/how-hard-did-you-look-equivalence-and-non-inferiority/</guid>
      <description>I usually don’t read nutripharma articles outside the mainstream media, but someone tweeted a link about saffron, which apparently cures everything. The last straw was a line beginning  “Saffron, a major component of the Mediterranean diet…”
 Saffron can’t really be described as a major component of anything, even risotto milanese, and it’s not unique to the Mediterranean region: it’s a well-known spice in India, Pakistan, Iran. And it’s not just the well-known places: England produced saffron before Italy produced tomatoes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Clinically proven ingredients</title>
      <link>/2015/02/26/clinically-proven-ingredients/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2015/02/26/clinically-proven-ingredients/</guid>
      <description>NZ golf prodigy Lydia Ko has a sponsorship deal with a company that sells special jetlag-reducing water. She obviously knows how this sort of thing works, and what she said to the Herald was nicely crafted
 Ms Ko said she was excited to have the support of 1Above.
“I haven’t really taken it for a long-haul flight before but I’ve seen some of the results and everything that comes with it and I have heard great things,” she said.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Science and statistical inference</title>
      <link>/2015/02/17/science-and-statistical-inference/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2015/02/17/science-and-statistical-inference/</guid>
      <description>Q: There have been a lot of papers recently about the spike in p-values just below 0.05, haven’t there?
A: Yes. A bit depressing. But there’s a new analysis that says it’s ok.
Q: Really? That’s great!
A: Yes, Daniel Lakens shows that you can explain the recent increase in just-significant p-values, and that “data does not provide any indication of an increase in questionable research practices”
Q: And is his modelling correct?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Assumptions and testing</title>
      <link>/2015/01/15/assumptions-and-testing/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2015/01/15/assumptions-and-testing/</guid>
      <description>My attention was drawn on Twitter to an old (1999) paper in The American Statistician, “Different Outcomes of the Wilcoxon-Mann-Whitney Test from Different Statistics Packages.” The authors looked at 11 statistics packages and found they didn’t always give the same result for the Wilcoxon/Mann-Whitney test. The big problem was handling of tied observations.
Here are their example data:
 The authors say “It is obvious that the data resulting from the experiment could not be analyzed by the Student’s t-test.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A transitive test is a test for a univariate parameter</title>
      <link>/2015/01/14/a-transitive-test-is-a-test-for-a-univariate-parameter/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2015/01/14/a-transitive-test-is-a-test-for-a-univariate-parameter/</guid>
      <description>As you know, rank tests can be non-transitive: they can have the rock-paper-scissors property. Tests that are for a single real-valued summary statistic (eg a test comparing means or medians or variance) are always transitive, because they are just comparing a single number, and ordering on numbers is transitive.
The converse is almost obviously almost true: if you have a transitive test, it almost has to be a test for a single real-valued summary statistic.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New header picture</title>
      <link>/2015/01/12/new-header-picture/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2015/01/12/new-header-picture/</guid>
      <description>As you can see, there’s a new header picture to replace the generic tumblr theme. It’s a pair of Superb Fairywrens, aka blue wrens (Malurus cyaneus), one of my favourite Melbourne birds. They’re now quite common along the Melbourne coastline from St Kilda down along the bay.
For people in the Northern hemisphere: these are completely unrelated to the wrens you are familiar with, and are also unrelated to the New Zealand wrens.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomato, tomato</title>
      <link>/2015/01/12/tomato-tomato/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2015/01/12/tomato-tomato/</guid>
      <description>There are two* great commandments for conference session chairs
You shall adhere to the schedule with all your heart and all your mind and all your strength You shall pronounce the speakers’ names approximately as they do themselves  For show-biz award ceremonies the first commandment doesn’t apply, but the second still does.
In order to pronounce someone’s name correctly, you need to ask for the correct pronunciation and have some way of remembering it, such as writing it down phonetically.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Different questions can have different answers</title>
      <link>/2015/01/11/different-questions-can-have-different-answers/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2015/01/11/different-questions-can-have-different-answers/</guid>
      <description>The Slate Money podcast [1] had an item on Manhattan apartment prices. The mean price last quarter was $1.7 million and the median was \$0.98 million. Firstly, that’s a lot of money. Secondly, the mean is a lot bigger than the median. The real point, though, is that the mean is a record, up on the previous peak (in 2008) by $120,000. The median is down from 2008, by $15,000.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Variation explained and log transformation</title>
      <link>/2015/01/03/variation-explained-and-log-transformation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2015/01/03/variation-explained-and-log-transformation/</guid>
      <description>This post is technical details for one at StatsChat on the Johns Hopkins “two-thirds of cancer is bad luck” paper.
I don’t have any real opinions on the conclusion: it’s clear that unforced errors in DNA copying will cause some cancers, and it’s not obvious how many. The technical problem with the paper (or at least with its publicity) is that the ‘proportion of variation explained’ was estimated for log risk and quoted as “two-thirds of cancers are due to bad luck’.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How not to treat Ebola</title>
      <link>/2014/12/23/how-not-to-treat-ebola/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/12/23/how-not-to-treat-ebola/</guid>
      <description>From the Guardian, via Mark Henderson of the Wellcome Trust
 Ebola patients at a treatment centre in Sierra Leone have been given a heart drug that is untested against the virus in animals and humans, a move that has been deemed reckless by one senior scientist and has prompted UK medical staff at the centre to leave.
 Ebola is a problem for drug testing. You don’t want to leave people untreated, but you do want to find out as fast as possible what works.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Citations: credit or blame</title>
      <link>/2014/12/14/citations-credit-or-blame/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Dec 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/12/14/citations-credit-or-blame/</guid>
      <description>Katie Hinde at ‘Mammals Suck’ writes
 Only cite papers that you have read! DO NOT cite papers based on another publication’s report of them. Because every time that happens, a science fairy dies.
 That’s an excellent principle. So why do I have a paper in press that cites a paper I haven’t read?
There are two reasons to cite a paper: as evidence for a claim, or to give credit to the authors for their research.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What science should everyone know?</title>
      <link>/2014/12/08/what-science-should-everyone-know/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/12/08/what-science-should-everyone-know/</guid>
      <description>In response to the question “How much science knowledge should the average person have or should we just encourage people to ask questions?”
 @NaomiShadbolt @petergnz Basics: Atoms; Evolution; “the lights in the sky are suns”; Randomisation; Conservation laws. And ask questions.
— Thomas Lumley (@tslumley) December 8, 2014
 Expanding on this:
 Atoms: everything is made of a very large but not infinite number of definite, basically indivisible, pieces, and there are very few different types (about 100).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>It depends on what you mean by &#39;cost&#39;</title>
      <link>/2014/11/30/it-depends-on-what-you-mean-by-cost/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/11/30/it-depends-on-what-you-mean-by-cost/</guid>
      <description>The Tufts Center for the Study of Drug Development has a new cost estimate out: Cost to Develop and Win Marketing Approval for a New Drug Is $2.6 Billion.
The figure is probably fairly accurate as an estimate of what it’s trying to estimate, but it gets quoted in other contexts, so I think it’s worth looking at the number a piece at a time. The Tufts researchers haven’t provided enough information to do this, so I’m relying on estimates from Bruce Booth (who also has a spreadsheet that you can use for sensitivity analyses).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>This is just to say</title>
      <link>/2014/11/06/this-is-just-to-say/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/11/06/this-is-just-to-say/</guid>
      <description>The plums, which you stored there on ice,
I have eaten; they went in a trice.
If you meant them to last
For a morning repast
Then I’m sorry, but boy were they nice.
or
Some say the plums will end in tarts
Some say on ice
From what I’ve eaten ’round these parts
I hold with those who favor tarts
But if they had to vanish first
I think I know enough of guilt</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A people set apart</title>
      <link>/2014/11/05/a-people-set-apart/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/11/05/a-people-set-apart/</guid>
      <description>There’s a conference coming up at Deakin University in Melbourne, on energy drinks. The unusual aspect of the conference is that no-one who has received industry funding is welcome. Obviously the energy drink industry aren’t happy about this. I couldn’t give a fsck about their hurt feelings, but I hope this sort of policy doesn’t spread.
Now, I’m not completely naïve about the sorts of things some industry groups will do when there’s a lot of money at stake.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Miasma and Contagion</title>
      <link>/2014/10/25/miasma-and-contagion/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/10/25/miasma-and-contagion/</guid>
      <description>Scientists have a nasty habit of taking ordinary English words, turning them into technical terms, and then insisting that the ordinary use is Just Wrong. ‘Organic’, which I’ve written about before, is a good example.
On the other hand, sometimes the scientists are right. I complained on Twitter last night about the phrase ‘meningococcal virus’ in a Herald opinion piece on state housing, and I have previously complained about the ‘Psa virus’ for the bacterium Pseudomonas syringae pv.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Semiparametric efficiency and nearly-true models</title>
      <link>/2014/10/25/semiparametric-efficiency-and-nearly-true-models/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/10/25/semiparametric-efficiency-and-nearly-true-models/</guid>
      <description>Suppose you have \(N\) people with some variables measured, and you choose a subset of \(n\) to measure additional variables. I’m going to assume the probability \(\pi_i\) that you measure the additional variables on person \(i\) is known, so it has to be a setting where non-response isn’t an issue – eg, choosing which frozen blood samples to analyse, or which free-text questionnaire responses to code, or which medical records to pull for abstraction.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Broman&#39;s Socks and the Nature of Scientific Reporting</title>
      <link>/2014/10/20/bromans-socks-and-the-nature-of-scientific-reporting/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/10/20/bromans-socks-and-the-nature-of-scientific-reporting/</guid>
      <description>Rasmus Bååth wrote a post using Approximate Bayesian Computation to estimate a posterior distribution for Karl’s socks. What he didn’t consider was the impact of publication bias. In order for us to see the tweet, it was not only necessary that Karl’s first 11 socks were distinct, it was also necessary that he found this remarkable, and, probably, that no-one he follows on Twitter had made a similar laundry-related observation at any recent time.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is it good or bad when confounding adjustment makes no difference?</title>
      <link>/2014/09/24/is-it-good-or-bad-when-confounding-adjustment-makes-no-difference/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/09/24/is-it-good-or-bad-when-confounding-adjustment-makes-no-difference/</guid>
      <description>There’s a new paper out in J Epi Community Health, looking at the relationship between perceived job insecurity and incident asthma. NHS ‘Behind the Headlines’ covers it well.
One of the interesting things about the paper is that the crude relative risk between above/below 50% estimated risk of losing your job is 1.61, and the relative risks after adjustment in three increasingly-complex models are 1.58, 1.62, and 1.61. That is, the adjustment for confounding has no impact at all.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On dialect</title>
      <link>/2014/08/29/on-dialect/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Aug 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/08/29/on-dialect/</guid>
      <description>In New Zealand, ‘radiata’ and ‘macrocarpa’ are accepted common names for two widely planted non-native conifers: Pinus radiata and Cupressus macrocarpa, known in their native US as ‘Monterey pine’ and ‘Monterey cypress’ respectively.
It’s unusual for the specific epithet of a plant to become the common name. There are plenty of examples of the generic name becoming the common name, from ‘bougainvillea’ to ‘wisteria’. There are even plenty of examples where a former generic name has stuck as the common name after the botanists have renamed the plant to, eg, Pelargonium, Hippeastrum, or Corymbia.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rhetorical sensitivity analysis</title>
      <link>/2014/08/29/rhetorical-sensitivity-analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Aug 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/08/29/rhetorical-sensitivity-analysis/</guid>
      <description>Rhetorical sensitivity analysis “The ethanol in alcohol is a group one carcinogen, like asbestos,” Prof. Doug Sellman, Otago University (July 2013)
Professor Sellman is correct, of course. What’s more, alcohol is even an important cause of cancer. From the viewpoint of rhetoric and risk communication it’s still interesting to see how the effect of the sentence changes when other familiar IARC Group I carcinogens are substituted for ‘asbestos’
 alcohol is a group one carcinogen, like sunlight alcohol is a group one carcinogen, like birth-control pills alcohol is a group one carcinogen, like plutonium alcohol is a group one carcinogen, like tobacco alcohol is a group one carcinogen, like arsenic, alcohol is a group one carcinogen, like wood dust  None of these really has the quite same rhetorical impact; the only one that comes close is ‘tobacco’.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>O necessary sinpi</title>
      <link>/2014/08/27/o-necessary-sinpi/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Aug 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/08/27/o-necessary-sinpi/</guid>
      <description>The R help page for sin, cos, and tan, mentions functions sinpi, cospi, tanpi, “accurate for x which are multiples of a half.” This struck someone I know as strange. I’ve been thinking about this sort of thing recently while teaching Stat Computing, so here’s some background.
If you’re a mathematician, \(\sin x\) is given by a power series
\[\sin x = x - \frac{x^3}{3!}+\frac{x^5}{5!} -\frac{x^7}{7!} +-\cdots\]
This series converges for all \(x\), and so converges uniformly on any finite interval.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Taking meta-analysis heterogeneity seriously</title>
      <link>/2014/08/24/taking-meta-analysis-heterogeneity-seriously/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Aug 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/08/24/taking-meta-analysis-heterogeneity-seriously/</guid>
      <description>In fixed-effects meta-analysis of a set of trials the goal is to find a weighted average of the true treatment effects in those trials (whatever they might be). The results are summarised by the weighted average and a confidence interval reflecting its sampling uncertainty.
In random-effects meta-analysis the trials are modelled as an exchangeable sample, implying that they can be treated as coming independently from some latent distribution of true treatment effects.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Survey package update</title>
      <link>/2014/08/15/survey-package-update/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/08/15/survey-package-update/</guid>
      <description>There’s a new version, 3.30-3, of the ‘survey’ package for R. It’s got quite a lot of new stuff:
 AIC and BIC for generalised linear models Rank tests for more than two groups Logrank and generalised logrank tests  Since I’m known for a lack of enthusiasm about any of these techniques, why are they in the package? Am I just enabling?
Well, AIC and BIC are interesting, and I’ll say more below.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Feynman and the Suck Fairy</title>
      <link>/2014/07/12/feynman-and-the-suck-fairy/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Jul 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/07/12/feynman-and-the-suck-fairy/</guid>
      <description>There’s been a bit of…discussion…about Richard Feynman recently. In one Twitter conversation, Richard Easther said he had been thinking of using Feynman’s commencement address “Cargo Cult Science” with a first-year physics class, and had decided against.
I was a bit surprised. It’s been a long time since I read that piece, but I couldn’t remember anything objectionable in it. So I re-read it. It’s still really good in a lot of ways.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monotonicity and smoothness</title>
      <link>/2014/05/22/monotonicity-and-smoothness/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 May 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/05/22/monotonicity-and-smoothness/</guid>
      <description>Andrew Gelman has an interesting discussion of monotonicity as a modelling constraint. I basically agree with what he says, but since my first real statistical research (my M.Sc. thesis) was on order restrictions I thought I’d write about a related aspect of the problem.
Assuming that a relationship is monotone sounds like a very strong assumption, and therefore one that you’d expect to gain a lot by making. Asymptotically, this isn’t true.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Anchoring bias</title>
      <link>/2014/05/18/anchoring-bias/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 May 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/05/18/anchoring-bias/</guid>
      <description>Anchoring bias: high school students asked to add up the digits in their phone number and to estimate how many countries there are in Africa.
 (phew, it worked)
(I did delete one data point as non-responsive: estimated number of countries in Africa was 1)
(with adults I’d use last two digits of phone number, but with teenage girls I thought a bit more information-hiding was appropriate)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Randomisation without consent</title>
      <link>/2014/05/14/randomisation-without-consent/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/05/14/randomisation-without-consent/</guid>
      <description>The issue of randomisation without consent has come up in New Zealand. Because I’m on the HRC Data Monitoring Core Committee, which monitors some NZ clinical trials I don’t want to say much about any current NZ clinical trials, even ones we’re not monitoring. I do want to talk about the principle.
The always-useful NZ Science Media Centre has rounded up a couple of bioethicists on the topic, and you should read what they say.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Einstein, Wikiquote, and fact checking</title>
      <link>/2014/03/14/einstein-wikiquote-and-fact-checking/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Mar 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/03/14/einstein-wikiquote-and-fact-checking/</guid>
      <description>It’s not only Pi Day in the USA (3/14, they write dates backwards), it’s Einstein’s 135th birthday. Einstein, like Mark Twain, 孔夫子, Churchill, Disraeli, and the Chinese proverbs, is a quote magnet. He said many quotable things, and even more are attributed to him.
The NZ Herald has a list of ten Einstein quotes. Annoyingly, none of them say where or when they were said. So I did the absolutely minimal level of fact checking.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My likelihood depends on your frequency properties</title>
      <link>/2014/03/04/my-likelihood-depends-on-your-frequency-properties/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Mar 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/03/04/my-likelihood-depends-on-your-frequency-properties/</guid>
      <description>The likelihood principle states that given two hypotheses \(H_0\) and \(H_1\) and data \(X\), all the evidence regarding which hypothesis is true is contained in the likelihood ratio \[LR=\frac{P[X|H_1]}{P[X|H_0]}.\]
One of the fundamentals of scientific research is the idea of scientific publication, which allows other researchers to form their own conclusions based on your results and those of others. The data available to other researchers, and thus the likelihood on which they rely for inference, depends on your publication behaviour.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Chemical nerdview</title>
      <link>/2014/02/25/chemical-nerdview/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/02/25/chemical-nerdview/</guid>
      <description>One of Stephen J. Gould’s essays contains the admission
 I confess that I have always been greatly amused by the term primate, used in its ecclesiastical sense as “an archbishop … holding the first place among the bishops of a province.” My merriment must be shared by all zoologists, for primates, to us, are monkeys and apes–members of the order Primates. 
…
But this amusement is silly, parochial, and misguided.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>This is a wug. Now you have two of them.</title>
      <link>/2014/02/09/this-is-a-wug.-now-you-have-two-of-them./</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/02/09/this-is-a-wug.-now-you-have-two-of-them./</guid>
      <description>Three words that used to be plurals, and are changing in three different ways:
Candelabra used to be the plural of candelabrum, a multiple-armed candlestick holder. There are very few other English words ending in ‘brum’, and most of the words ending in ‘bra’ are singular (e.g. vertebra, penumbra, cobra, zebra, sabra, bra). Over time, candelabra has been used more and more often as the singular, perhaps most famously in the biographical movie “Behind the Candelabra” about Liberace; the corresponding plural is candelabras.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>At risk of vanishing</title>
      <link>/2013/12/14/at-risk-of-vanishing/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Dec 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/12/14/at-risk-of-vanishing/</guid>
      <description>A degree in science, in addition to specific facts about squid, neutrinos, or palladium-catalysed cross-couplings, should teach students what to do with questions about the world. In particular, they should learn to think about what the implications would be of each answer to the question, and know how we might use these implications to rule out some of the answers and reduce our uncertainty about others.
A degree in the humanities, in addition to specific facts about tenses in French, resource-allocation procedures in village societies, or the development of the Sangam literature, should teach students what to do with questions about the world.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Moving the goalposts?</title>
      <link>/2013/11/15/moving-the-goalposts/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/11/15/moving-the-goalposts/</guid>
      <description>There’s a paper in PNAS suggesting that lots of published scientific associations are likely to be false, and that Bayesian considerations imply a p-value threshold of 0.005 instead of 0.05 would be good. It’s had an impact outside the statistical world, eg, with a post on the blog Ars Technica. The motivation for the PNAS paper is a statistics paper showing how to relate p-values to Bayes Factors in some tests.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>From labhacks: the $25 scrunchable scientific poster</title>
      <link>/2013/11/04/from-labhacks-the-25-scrunchable-scientific-poster/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/11/04/from-labhacks-the-25-scrunchable-scientific-poster/</guid>
      <description>labhacks:
 image
 Printed on Spoonflower performance knit at 300 dpi. 36” x 56”, vivid colors, no unraveling, and minimal wrinkling, even after being stuffed in a backpack. Hangs straight with about 8 pins. Print cost is $22 with $3 shipping.
image
  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A diversity of gifts, but the same spirit</title>
      <link>/2013/10/30/a-diversity-of-gifts-but-the-same-spirit/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/10/30/a-diversity-of-gifts-but-the-same-spirit/</guid>
      <description>Peter Green used this line (from I Corinthians) for his Royal Statistical Society Presidential Address in 2003, which anyone interested in the future of statistics should read. I’ve been planning to steal it ever since then, and the time seems right.
Roger, Jeff, and Rafa at Simply Statistics are holding an unconference on the future of statistics, some time before dawn tomorrow morning New Zealand time. I probably won’t be attending, but if you’re in a more compatible time zone it promises to be interesting.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Interaction: &#39;real&#39; and statistical</title>
      <link>/2013/10/27/interaction-real-and-statistical/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/10/27/interaction-real-and-statistical/</guid>
      <description>Confounding is a model-independent property of nature: if doing A has a particular effect on Y, it is objectively either true or untrue that the conditional distributions of Y given A and not A match that particular effect. Interaction or effect modification is scale-dependent: you ask “is the effect of A on X in the presence of B the same as the effect of A on X in the absence of B.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Barren proxies</title>
      <link>/2013/10/20/barren-proxies/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/10/20/barren-proxies/</guid>
      <description>In causal inference it is often the case that you can’t obtain a confounding variable directly, you can only measure something that it affects. Judea Pearl correctly points out the danger of conditioning on a ‘barren proxy’ for a confounder, in situations like this one:
 A confounds the effect of B on C. D is affected by A but does not directly affect either B or C, so it is a ‘barren proxy’ for A.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Google completions and sexism</title>
      <link>/2013/10/18/google-completions-and-sexism/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/10/18/google-completions-and-sexism/</guid>
      <description>The new ads produced by UN Women illustrating widespread sexism using Google autocomplete are pretty chilling, eg,  The ads are convincing and what they imply is true, but I’m less sure that they are actually good evidence for what they imply.
Typing whole phrases into Google is not how I or people I’ve watched usually search. I type key words. The only reason I would search for a phrase such as “Women should not speak in church” would be to find the source.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Do you know where it&#39;s been?</title>
      <link>/2013/10/10/do-you-know-where-its-been/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/10/10/do-you-know-where-its-been/</guid>
      <description>Again this week on the bus I passed the annoying Phoenix Organics delivery van that says Don’t drink science, you don’t know where it’s been [ Phoenix are also notable for their aspartame scare page. ]
One of the things they don’t write up as glowingly is that they add the synthetic version of a natural antioxidant to their juices and their (naturally high-fructose) juice drinks, in unnaturally high concentrations. That’s perfectly legal by organic labelling rules, and the compound, ascorbic acid, is the same molecule as vitamin C – but we’re talking about an industry where ‘the same molecule’ doesn’t usually cut it as an excuse.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rock, paper, scissors, Wilcoxon test</title>
      <link>/2013/10/06/rock-paper-scissors-wilcoxon-test/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/10/06/rock-paper-scissors-wilcoxon-test/</guid>
      <description>Based on my nerdnite talk last week.
Transitivity is a basic property of orderings: if A is better than B and B is better than C, then A must be better than C. For example, if the All Blacks beat Tonga and Tonga beats Japan, we would expect the All Blacks to beat Japan.
Rock-paper-scissors is interesting because it is the opposite: if A beats B and B beats C then A must lose to C.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Today we have shaming of prats</title>
      <link>/2013/10/06/today-we-have-shaming-of-prats/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/10/06/today-we-have-shaming-of-prats/</guid>
      <description>Background: Revenge, ego, and corruption in Wikipedia
Today we have shaming of prats. Yesterday, we had unclear sources, and tomorrow morning
we may have original research. But today, Today we have shaming of prats. The Flame Robin 
is a small passerine bird native to Australia,
and today we have shaming of prats
This is the anonymous editor. And this
is the revenge edit, whose use you will see
when you are snubbed by an author.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Auckland&#39;s top news story</title>
      <link>/2013/10/03/aucklands-top-news-story/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/10/03/aucklands-top-news-story/</guid>
      <description>Background: The Herald has had a whole sequence of stories, including two on the front page, about the decision of the city council to stop mowing the ‘berms’, the strips of grass between the road and sidewalk. 
Additional background: the Mayor of Auckland is one Len Brown.
O Lenny Boy, the berms, the berms need mowing
From Glen to Lynn, and down Mt Eden side
The winter’s gone, and all the grass is growing</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Statins and the causal Markov property</title>
      <link>/2013/09/23/statins-and-the-causal-markov-property/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/09/23/statins-and-the-causal-markov-property/</guid>
      <description>A real example: there is developing uncertainty that the statin class of cholesterol-lowering drugs really works by lowering LDL cholesterol. This is partly because other drugs (eg, ezetimibe) that lower LDL cholesterol don’t have the same impact on heart attacks, and also because statins seem to have beneficial effects on too many other conditions. In principle, you could control for achieved cholesterol levels and see if statin use was then conditionally independent of heart disease [adjust and see if the effect goes away].</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PBRF consultation response consultation</title>
      <link>/2013/09/22/pbrf-consultation-response-consultation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/09/22/pbrf-consultation-response-consultation/</guid>
      <description>Friday week (October 4) is the deadline for providing input to the consultation on changes in the PBRF process (for foreigners: the national research evaluation program that allocates a chunk of long-term research funding to universities). Here’s the consultation document, if you haven’t read it yet.
This is what I’m planning to say. It’s also open for public feedback.
Background: I was a member of the PBRF MIST review panel, and also submitted a portfolio.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An absolutely minimal way to increase invited speaker diversity</title>
      <link>/2013/09/13/an-absolutely-minimal-way-to-increase-invited-speaker-diversity/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/09/13/an-absolutely-minimal-way-to-increase-invited-speaker-diversity/</guid>
      <description>The low proportion of women among invited speakers at conferences has finally become an issue in biology and computing and science fiction (at least for the people in my Twitter feed).
You might worry, if you were running a conference, that having some sort of minimum standard for diversity might lead to suboptimal speakers, or if you had a bunch of small sessions, might be difficult to ensure in each session.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What I said on StatsChat only shorter and with more swearing</title>
      <link>/2013/09/04/what-i-said-on-statschat-only-shorter-and-with-more-swearing/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/09/04/what-i-said-on-statschat-only-shorter-and-with-more-swearing/</guid>
      <description>Stealing a Keith Ng title, to do a post motivated by his criticism of my StatsChat post as a ‘generous interpretation’ of Bill English.
English said that households with income below $110000 collectively paid no net income tax. This assumes that all benefits are paid solely from income tax, not GST, and even then has to lump together people who receive more in benefits than they pay in income taxes with a lot of people who pay much more in income tax than they receive in benefits.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On the persistence of variation in horn size among Soay sheep</title>
      <link>/2013/08/23/on-the-persistence-of-variation-in-horn-size-among-soay-sheep/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/08/23/on-the-persistence-of-variation-in-horn-size-among-soay-sheep/</guid>
      <description>(BBC News)
The small-horned rams are fitter, but the big-horned rams are phatter
And though we deemed it sweeter
To dally with the latter,
The small horns still stay with us
To Scottish boffins’ wonder;
In flocks the nerds still pull the birds
When the jocks are six feet under
(After Peacock)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A layperson&#39;s view of a science communication problem</title>
      <link>/2013/08/13/a-laypersons-view-of-a-science-communication-problem/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/08/13/a-laypersons-view-of-a-science-communication-problem/</guid>
      <description>There’s a story in one of the NZ papers saying that Fonterra and the government are completely wrong about the source of the botulism contamination in milk products and about how to fix it.
This is a field I know very little about, so it’s interesting to look at the story just from the point of view of an educated consumer.
There are some stylistic points that make the story look like it could be bogus: the claim that this one guy is right and everyone else is wrong, the reference to “sitting on material that will embarrass Fonterra further”, blaming the problem on glyphosate (evil Monsanto’s evil Roundup herbicide), the lack of any links or details for the research, and the lack of any independent scientific opinion.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SPEED sessions at JSM 2013</title>
      <link>/2013/08/09/speed-sessions-at-jsm-2013/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/08/09/speed-sessions-at-jsm-2013/</guid>
      <description>This year, the Joint Statistical Meetings introduced a combined poster/short presentation session. The sessions took up a half-day, twice as long as the typical session. In the first half, each presenter gave a 5-minute talk, and the second session was an electronic poster session. I signed up for one of these sessions primarily because I think any form of innovation at the Joint Statistical Meetings should be supported. For people who haven’t experienced the JSM, it’s the largest gathering of statisticians in the world, but it is also characterised by rigid and apparently inexplicable rules (eg, if the chair for your session doesn’t show, you are supposed to find a replacement who isn’t chairing any other session in the whole conference) and a significant minority of astoundingly awful talks.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>In defense of theory</title>
      <link>/2013/08/08/in-defense-of-theory/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/08/08/in-defense-of-theory/</guid>
      <description>The statistical community, and even more so the statistical curriculum, hasn’t yet adapted fully to the improvements in computing over the past few decades, and so still gives too much priority to mathematical approaches and too little to computational approaches to many problems. That’s one reason for the popularity of the term ‘data science’, and for the mixed feelings about Nate Silver’s comment at his JSM address that ‘data scentist is just a sexed-up term for statistician’.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Some failure modes of statistics research talks</title>
      <link>/2013/08/04/some-failure-modes-of-statistics-research-talks/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/08/04/some-failure-modes-of-statistics-research-talks/</guid>
      <description>Written before #JSM2013 actually starts, so it’s not about your talk there.
Also, this is about deliberate choices by the presenter, and specifically about statistics research talks. “The Overgeneralized Beta Distribution”. There is a place for new parametric distributions, but it’s a fairly small place and mostly occupied by distributions derived from underlying substantive knowledge.
 “Asymptotics of an uninteresting estimator”. If there were a novel mathematical idea this would be fine, but otherwise we know its asymptotic behavior and roughly why it happens, and we can’t read your notation fast enough anyway.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Graphs and counterfactuals</title>
      <link>/2013/07/15/graphs-and-counterfactuals/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jul 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/07/15/graphs-and-counterfactuals/</guid>
      <description>The two main ways of reasoning about cause and effect in statistics are causal graphs and counterfactuals.
With causal graphs, you write down variables and draw arrows representing direct effects of one variable on another, and then work with a set of axioms that summarise what it means for one variable to affect another. With counterfactuals, you talk about the effect of a variable in terms of the difference between the actual outcome with the variable set one way and the ‘potential outcome’ if it had been set another way.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Welfare as an addictive drug</title>
      <link>/2013/07/15/welfare-as-an-addictive-drug/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jul 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/07/15/welfare-as-an-addictive-drug/</guid>
      <description>From the NZ Herald today Doctors have been told that putting patients on welfare is akin to putting them on “an addictive debilitating drug … not dissimilar to smoking”.
Smoking is a really, really bad analogy here, since doctors would absolutely never recommend a patient starts smoking. It’s hard to imagine how someone with a medical degree could come up with that analogy. Welfare is hard to get off and probably bad for your health, but a better comparison would be something like sleeping pills or opioid analgesics: drugs that are risky, potentially dependence-inducing, and should be taken for the shortest possible time period, but that are absolutely medically necessary at times.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Big data linear models</title>
      <link>/2013/07/08/big-data-linear-models/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jul 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/07/08/big-data-linear-models/</guid>
      <description>The biglm package for R currently uses incremental QR decomposition, which fits linear models to big data in linear time and bounded memory, but doesn’t parallelize.
It turns out that parallel computation is easy (and has been studied by Dongarra and the LAPACK folks). If you have two data chunks reduced to \(R_1\) and \(Q_1^TY_1\), and \(R_2\) and \(Q_2^TY_2\), just treat each \(R\) as an \(X\) and each \(Q^TY\) as a \(Y\) to merge the QR decompositions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sparse linear systems and calibration of weights</title>
      <link>/2013/07/08/sparse-linear-systems-and-calibration-of-weights/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jul 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/07/08/sparse-linear-systems-and-calibration-of-weights/</guid>
      <description>Diego Zardetto (Italian national stats agency) wants to be able to calibrate sampling weights to population totals for regions. This leads to a very large number of calibration variables and solving large linear systems.
Using the Matrix package in R, we can compute sparse QR decompositions instead of the dense ones used in the survey package. Alternatively, using block-diagonal sparse matrices from the bdsmatrix package we can represent the linear system as a set of separate systems for each region.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Problems with faithfulness and the causal Markov property (II)</title>
      <link>/2013/07/06/problems-with-faithfulness-and-the-causal-markov-property-ii/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Jul 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/07/06/problems-with-faithfulness-and-the-causal-markov-property-ii/</guid>
      <description>This one I got from reading Nancy Cartwright’s Hunting Causes, and using them, though it isn’t exactly the point she’s making. It’s also related to points made by Hofstadter, Dennett, and others about reductionist reasoning. The idea of causal graphs is that you have variables and some prior knowledge of possible causal relationships between them – the prior knowledge could be as weak as ‘future cannot cause past’ or could incorporate a lot of domain-specific knowledge.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Problems with faithfulness and the causal Markov property (I)</title>
      <link>/2013/07/02/problems-with-faithfulness-and-the-causal-markov-property-i/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jul 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/07/02/problems-with-faithfulness-and-the-causal-markov-property-i/</guid>
      <description>The causal Markov property says that you can write down causal relationships between variables in a directed acyclic graph so that each variable is affected only by its parents in the graph. The faithfulness property says that the variables will have exactly the conditional independence properties required by the graph.
The first problem with these properties is measurement error. If the only causal relations are that A affects B and C, then B and C are conditionally independent given A.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Upcoming talks and stuff</title>
      <link>/2013/06/30/upcoming-talks-and-stuff/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Jun 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/06/30/upcoming-talks-and-stuff/</guid>
      <description>Two modules (on intermediate and advanced R) with Ken Rice at the Seattle Summer Institute in Statistical Genetics
Joint Statistical Meetings: analyzing large data with SQL generated by R, with Hannes Muhleisen. MonetDB is a database optimised for analysis tasks, and controlling it from R gives more flexibility and programmability. </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Two simple notes on error in regression models</title>
      <link>/2013/06/28/two-simple-notes-on-error-in-regression-models/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Jun 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/06/28/two-simple-notes-on-error-in-regression-models/</guid>
      <description>In regression, we often talk about the difference between the population line and the observations as “errors.” In some introductory texts these are even called “measurement errors” in Y. Sometimes they are errors in Y, and sometimes they are even measurement errors in Y, but much more often Y is the truth and the ‘error’ is the error in predicting Y by a straight line. As Dan Davies observed (from memory) “The Great Depression really happened; it wasn’t just an unusually inaccurate observation of an underlying 4% return on equities”</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>When is Bayesian introductory statistics better?</title>
      <link>/2013/06/27/when-is-bayesian-introductory-statistics-better/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Jun 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/06/27/when-is-bayesian-introductory-statistics-better/</guid>
      <description>For the sort of statistics taught in introductory courses, competent Bayesian and frequentist analysis are going to agree – point and interval estimates will be similar, and similar conclusions will be drawn. Computation isn’t seriously hard for either approach, though prepackaged pointy-clicky software is more available for frequentist inference. There are going to be pedagogical differences. The big one, in favour of Bayesian statistics, is not having to explain p-values. Another benefit of the Bayesian approach is that it gives you a good reason not to talk about rank tests.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My Setup</title>
      <link>/2013/06/08/my-setup/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Jun 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/06/08/my-setup/</guid>
      <description>For UsesThis.com, prompted by Luis Apiolaza.
Who are you, and what do you do?
I’m a statistics professor at the University of Auckland. I teach, do research in statistics and in epidemiology, and contribute to R.
What hardware do you use?
I’ve been using Mac laptops since 2001. I currently have an aluminium MacBook from 2009 and am waiting on delivery of an 11in MacBook Air. They are nicely solid, have reasonable keyboards, run Unix, and support the Microsoft software that my collaborators use.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hello World</title>
      <link>/2013/06/07/hello-world/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Jun 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/06/07/hello-world/</guid>
      <description>Hello, world This will be my not-StatsChat blog, for things that are too technical, too political, or simply not relevant to StatsChat.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Talks in the near future</title>
      <link>/2013/06/07/talks-in-the-near-future/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Jun 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2013/06/07/talks-in-the-near-future/</guid>
      <description>“Filtering for rare variant tests” CHARGE consortium workshop, Rotterdam. Basic message: it’s total count of rare alleles that matters.
“R: an environment for statistical computing and graphics”. CWI, Amsterdam. Talking about the history, design, and applications of R to a scary computer-science audience.
“Testing rare DNA variants in unrelated individuals: experience from the CHARGE consortium”, IARC, Lyon. On unidirectional and omnidirectional ‘burden of mutation’ tests using rare DNA variants.
“Analysing very large surveys with SQL generated from R” ITACOSM conference, Milan.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lorem Ipsum</title>
      <link>/1520/01/01/lorem-ipsum/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 1520 13:09:13 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/1520/01/01/lorem-ipsum/</guid>
      <description>Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetur adipiscing elit, sed do eiusmod tempor incididunt ut labore et dolore magna aliqua. Ut enim ad minim veniam, quis nostrud exercitation ullamco laboris nisi ut aliquip ex ea commodo consequat. Duis aute irure dolor in reprehenderit in voluptate velit esse cillum dolore eu fugiat nulla pariatur. Excepteur sint occaecat cupidatat non proident, sunt in culpa qui officia deserunt mollit anim id est laborum.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>